Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin 1787-1790 Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    News of his ill health received from Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson; affairs in France; energy and prudence shown by a Nation accused of volatility; incredible revolution which has taken place; the yoke of priests, nobles and King shaken off; the Nation mistress of her fate; all this accomplished without bloodshed; America's example a great help and inspiration; Marquis de la Fayette chosen to command the bourgeois militia of Paris [National Guard]; storming of the bastille; M. [Jean Sylvain] Bailly Mayor of Paris; lawless acts by bands of ruffians driven out of Paris; himself, commands the militia of Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Young, Moses. Bordeaux
    Introducing Col. [John Skey] Eustace of New York, who desires to transmit to Franklin some important papers relative to the Revolution in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Acknowledging receipt of American newspapers; reports of Franklin's illness; question of reducing the two reluctant States to join the other eleven; considers the Mississippi a noble boundary; desires Franklin's opinion on equal taxation and other transactions of Congress. Account of an illness from which he is just convalescing. Weather conditions and crops. His views on affairs in France; honorable action of the Duke of Orleans and the Archbishop of Bordeaux; can boast no such virtuous ecclesiastics in Ireland. Damage done by the heavy rains. Denounces the present Viceroy, ([George Nugent-Temple-Grenville, Duke of] Buckingham); certain unpromising conditions in Ireland. News of a bloody revolution in France; sums up the main events; French refugees in Dublin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Kluseman, Fr. William. Philadelphia
    His reasons for leaving Prussia and coming to America; account of his business ventures and losses; present plan to keep a little shop in Philadelphia; all his hopes crushed by being sued for an old debt of five pounds; begs Franklin to assist him to pay this sum and so put him on his feet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Arthaud, Charles. Au Cap François
    Sending him a work on mineral waters published by their club [Le Cercle des Philadelphes].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Wright, John. London
    Franklin's essay [Address to the Inhabitants of the United States on the Disaffection that has prevailed towards the New System of Government introduced in that Country] published in the Gentleman's Magazine for February. Hopes to see the new Constitution established through all the States; Dr. [Richard] Price's opinion that the world is not yet good enough for a democratic government; believes that the world grows better and better; instances the efforts made to abolish slavery. France bordering on famine and civil war; Marquis de la Fayette at the head of the populace; report that the Comte d'Artois, who escaped from the fury of the mob at Paris, has erected his standard in Flanders. Delighted to hear that Franklin is writing his memoirs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Blardierres, Delaunay des
    Sends a copy of a letter from M. Saugrain de Vigny to M. de Lassize; no further doubt conceivable of M. Picque's death; authentic proof needed however in order to settle M. Picque's estate and carry out his will; applies to Franklin for the necessary data; begs him to have the possessions of the deceased forwarded to France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Ellicott, Andrew. New York
    Concerning a bill before Congress for the appointment of a Geographer for the United States, and a Surveyor-General for the Western Territory; has made application for the office; begs Franklin to write a letter in his favor to the President of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August 8; A.L.S 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Affairs in France; M. [Jean Sylvain] Bailly is Chief Magistrate of Paris; Marquis de la Fayette, Commander-in-Chief of the Militia; all the Provinces aping the example of the Capital; the King's surrender to the will of the National Assembly, who, having calmed all commotions, are busy framing a Constitution; America quoted as an example.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Affairs in France; spirited and liberal measures passed by the National Assembly; universal tolerance, etc.; all disturbances appear to be quieting down.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Question of Mr. [John] Tyler's legacy; extract on the subject from Mr. William Russell's letter. Books forwarded to Franklin; unable to get the Gentleman's Magazine further back than 1783. Refers Franklin for French news to the numerous published accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 August; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Condoles with him on the painful state of his health. Delighted that he will see the fruits of liberty diffused through the nations of mankind; the rights of mankind to liberty and free government acknowledged as of divine origin. Origin of the revolution in France. His hope of a future close union of England and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 6; A.L.S. 6p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Mrs. [Jane] Mecom in better health and spirits. News of Mrs. [Elizabeth] Partridge, Gov. [James] Bowdoin and Col. Ingersoll. Describing the kind of mystical philosophy to which his father was converted in 1772; bad effect on his business; his mother determined to take in boarders; his brother Jack's business in Philadelphia. Disposition made of the books which Franklin desired sold.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Amazing revolution in France; sums up the various startling events there; admires the Duc de la Rochefoucauld's speech in favor of a free press; depicts the humiliating situation of the King of France. Ireland's admiration for the Marquis de la Fayette. Thinks England will soon be involved in a war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    French affairs; list of articles under debate in the National Assembly. Explains the advantage to America could she export wheat to Europe this year on her own account; the crops in France will fall far short of the demand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Patterson, Robert. Philadelphia
    The meeting of the [American] Philosophical Society will take place at Franklin's house, if that will permit his being present; if he cannot attend, the meeting will be held at their Hall on Fifth street, which is in some degree prepared for their reception.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Washington, George. New York
    Expressions of friendship for him and of sympathy for his sufferings; assuring him of the admiration and veneration of the entire Nation.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 396; Bigelow, X, 148).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Sending a copy of a letter from Mr. Garbutt together with his answer; hopes Mr. John Tyler will immediately take the necessary steps to pay his debts and release his legacy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward
    Radical Resolutions of the National Assembly, limiting the power of the King; Ireland in the great suspense; dissolution of present Parliament expected; rumors as to the Viceroy's return; the promise he has violated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 September 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Hay, Hannah. Philadelphia
    Begging his assistance to recover certain property, for which she has tried these two years past to obtain a settlement; wishes to return to her children and friends in England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 October 8; A.L.S. 2p.; West, Benjamin. London
    Introducing their ingenious countryman, Mr. John Trumbull, one of the foremost of living artists, who is about to do some work in his native country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 October 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    About to sail for Richmond; hopes to fix the true course of the western edge of the gulf stream. Money received from the sale of his books.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Small, Alexander. Newent, England
    Sending him a work on bees by Mr. Buter; peculiarities in orthography which has deterred many from reading it; suggests that he reprint and publish it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Hays, Getlah. New York
    Decease of her husband, Solomon Hays, whom Franklin will probably recollect; has great difficulty in getting along, owing to various money losses; complains of being both old and poor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de, fils
    Will abide by Franklin's counsel and remain in America; has written his father to that effect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Broom, Jacob. Wilmington
    The debt due Franklin by Jacob A. Killen; no difficulty in having the bond renewed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Account of his money losses. Blessings he has enjoyed through life. Affectionate relations between himself and his Aunt [Jane] Mecom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Trumbull, Jno. New York
    Enclosing Franklin a letter from his friend Benjamin West; looks upon Franklin as his patron; has begun a series of pictures treating of the great events of the Revolution, hence his presence in America; hopes he can count on Franklin's approbation and protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Killen, William. Dover, Delaware
    Unavoidable delay in paying Franklin a debt contracted by his son [Jacob A. Killen]; sends sixty pounds; begs to be informed if that amount does not fully cover the principal and interest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 November 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Bedford, Gunning Jr. Wilmington
    Papers of Mr. Parker in much confusion; fortunately found the one Franklin wanted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Ramsay, David. Charleston
    Returning the History of Lord North's Administration, which was placed by mistake among his books. Expressing gratitude for favors received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 December 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Merwin, Miles. Philadelphia
    Desires permission to dedicate to Franklin his History of the United States, for which he was kind enough to subscribe; encloses the dedication for any corrections Franklin may see fit to make.
    E. by Franklin. Sensible of the honor done him but cannot consent to the publication of such excessive enconiums of his conduct; hopes Mr. Merwin will pardon his refusal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Parkinson, George. Philadelphia
    Desires to explain an invention of his own for spinning hemp, flax and wool into yarn; thinks it may prove of general utility to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 December 27; L .S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Amsterdam
    The enclosed documents from the Count de Ségur will partly explain his reasons for leaving Russia; dark intrigues and mean subterfuges to which he was exposed by Asiatic jealousy and malice; wishes such use to be made of the enclosed papers as to justify him in the eyes of his friends in America; expects to remain some time longer in Europe; thinks the Baltic will witness warmer work than it has yet done. Has sent the Empress his journal to show her how she has been deceived by his enemies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1789.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Shaw, John
    A request for aid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1789?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Story, Enoch Jr
    Sending him a volume of poems by William Smith, Attorney at Law, of Pennsylvania. About to publish the travels of Mr. [William] Bartram, botanist; encloses proposals and hopes it will meet with his approbation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 January 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Perkins, James Jr. Boston
    Concerning the 11th Article in the treaty between France and America, namely, that the subjects of the United States shall not be reputed aliens in France and are exempted from the droits d'aubaine; this has been made to apply solely to the Continental dominions of France; the French Colonies denied its benefits; their estates confiscated on their decease; desires to know the true significance of the said Article; his interest in Saint Domingo his excuse for this request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 January 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Barton, William. Philadelphia
    Reminds Franklin that he possesses several papers which he intended to communicate to the American Philosophical Society; a meeting to be held that evening, if Franklin is not too much indisposed he may desire to make the communication then.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 February 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Pemberton, James. Philadelphia
    Enclosing two copies of a memorial by the Pennsylvania Society for promoting the Abolition of Slavery; requests Franklin, as President of the Society, to forward one to the President of the Senate and the other to the Speaker of the House of Representatives.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 February 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Redick, David. Philadelphia
    Returning the letters, etc., with which he favored him; pleased to find a French nobleman so democratic; surprised that France should take America rather than England as an example; puts that down to Franklin's influence; his appreciation of Franklin's esteem and his conviction of his own unworthiness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 March 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de, fils
    His father's accounts with the United States not yet finally settled; wishes to hasten matters in order to return to France; begs Franklin to add a line to the enclosed letter to Mr. [Edmund] Randolph, if he thinks it will help; his father still at Chaumont, refusing to settle his business or sell any of his property before the writer's return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 March 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Preaud, L. Mâcon France
    Death of his brother-in-law, Honoré Girond, in North Carolina; desires Franklin's influence to obtain from the French Consul, the settlement of his brother's estate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 March 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Peters, Richard. Philadelphia
    Concerning a bill before the House on an application of John Churchman; a letter from Mr. [Nevil] Maskelyne to Franklin said to contain some material information; begs Franklin to send the letter or an extract from it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 April 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Annoucing the death of his wife; her many admirable qualities; his Aunt [Jane] Mecom much shaken by this loss.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1790 April 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Peters, Richard. Philadelphia
    Returning Mr. [Nevil] Maskelyne's letter.